Finding Aid for Donald A. Kimball Architectural Drawings and Photographs 1935-1954
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Donald A. Kimball Architectural Drawings and Photographs 1935-1954
Kimball, Donald A., 1907-1998.
8 oversized folders and .25 linear ft.
Saginaw based Michigan architect; 1929 graduate of University of Michigan's School of Architecture. Designed a variety of private and public buildings in the 1940s and early 1950s, mainly in mid and northern Michigan. Collection comprised of six pencil and watercolor renderings, sixty-three measured working drawings, and twenty-two black and white photographs.
9857 Aa 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The material was donated by Jane A. Kimball (donor no. 8714 ) in April of 1998.
The collection is open for research.
Donald A. Kimball, the eldest son of Eva and Chester Kimball, was born in Saginaw, Michigan on September 9, 1907. After graduation from Saginaw High School, he studied architecture at the University of Michigan, earning a B. S. degree in Architecture in 1929. After an additional year of graduate studies, he worked briefly for an architectural firm in Saginaw before starting an architectural practice in his home city. Kimball had a distinguished architectural career, designing a wide variety of private and public buildings throughout Michigan in the late 30s, 40s and early 50s. In addition, he served on a committee appointed by the Governor of Michigan to write a new building code for the state and was vice-president of the Michigan Society of Architects and president of the American Institute of Architects of the Saginaw Valley.
Kimball married Dorothy Bartlett in 1935, and she became his lifelong partner in both his professional and his family life. In 1954, they moved to Hope Ranch in Santa Barbara, and in 1973 into a house he built across from the Santa Barbara Mission and Rose Garden. He continued to practice while in California, designing several houses and an addition to the First Congregational Church. Donald Kimball died in 1998 at the age of 90. He had a daughter, Jane and a son, Andrew.
The Donald A. Kimball collection (7 oversized folders and .25 linear ft., 1935-1954) is a concentrated and fine example of the work of a Michigan architect practicing largely in mid and northern Michigan during the late 30s through the mid 50s. The collection is comprised wholly of visual architectural material representative of the spirit of the times. Researchers should note that an additional Kimball collection is held at Central Michigan University in the Clarke Historical Library.
There are three series in the collection: Renderings (6 boards, 1935-1946 and undated); Architectural Drawings (63 drawings for 6 projects, 1936-1954); and Photographs (22 prints, undated). There is some overlap between the series. For example, there are items representing Saginaw's Michigan Bean Company in each of the series; and there are both drawings and photographs for WSAM Radio Station, also a Saginaw building.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Kimball, Donald A., 1907-1998.; Architects--Michigan--Saginaw.; Architecture--Michigan.; Architecture, Domestic--Michigan.; Dwellings--Michigan--Saginaw.; Business enterprises--Michigan.; Architectural photographs.; Architectural drawings.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.
- Renderings
  Renderings, effectively executed in pencil and watercolor, well illustrate the range of building types generated in Kimball's office, from suburban residences to offices and factories. When considered together, the Michigan Bean Company, Great Lakes Greyhound Bus Station and Restaurant, downtown storefront, office building, and two distinctly different residences, provide a glimpse into the built environment typical to a midwestern community of this era.
  - Residence, 1935, pencil, colored pencil, white paint on board (Folder 1)
  - Residence, October 1941, black and white watercolor on green board (Folder 1)
  - Michigan Bean Company [Saginaw, Mich.], 1945, pencil and watercolor on board (Folder 1)
  - Bus Station (Great Lakes Greyhound Lines) and Restaurant [Mackinaw, Mich.], pencil and watercolor on board (Folder 2)
  - Downtown Storefront, 1946, pencil and watercolor on board (Folder 2)
  - 505 Eddy Building, pencil, colored pencil and watercolor on board (Folder 2)
- Architectural Drawings
  Architectural Drawings are all original, measured working drawings, including floor plans, elevations, details and sections. Six projects are represented-- a personal Kimball residence, a bus station, a service station, a radio station, a bean factory and a pickle and canning company. Most drawings are pencil on linen, although there a few pencil drawings on tracing paper.
  - No. 164 / Mr. & Mrs. Donald Kimball, 1936, 4 drawings (Folder 3)
  - No. 246 / Service Station for Mr. Maurice E. Brown, Saginaw, Mich., 1940, 7 drawings (Folder 4)
  - No. 4900 / Radio Station WSAM, Saginaw, Mich., 1948, 2 drawings (Folder 5)
  - Nos. 316; 4904; 5018 / Michigan Bean Company, Saginaw, Mich., 1944-1950, 22 drawings (Folder 6)
  - No. 4502 / Bus Station and Garage Building; Great Lakes Greyhound Lines, Inc., Mackinaw, Mich., 1946, 11 drawings (Folder 7)
  - Nos. 5405; 5215 / Daily Pickle and Canning Company, Saginaw, Mich., 1951-1954, 17 drawings (Folder 8)
- Photographs
  Photographs (all in black and white), while unfortunately undated and unidentified, provide evidence of Kimball's diverse interests and ability to respond to client preferences. Researchers interested in documentation of neighborhoods of the 40s and 50s -- in particular, movie theaters, service stations, supermarkets, and factories in midsize midwestern cities, will find many images of value. The series also includes seven residences, ranging from variations on the suburban ranch to the fifties modern and the familiar traditional. In addition, there are three images of Kimball at professional gatherings with colleagues.
  - Commercial
    - Household Finance (Box 1)
    - Goes Seeds (Box 1)
    - Michigan Bean Company (Box 1)
    - Office Building (Box 1)
    - Peet Community Center (Box 1)
    - Phillips Service Station (Box 1)
    - Ray's Food Fair (Box 1)
    - Royal Movie Theater (Box 1)
    - Schaubel News Co (Box 1)
    - Storefront (S. Michigan and Adams) (Box 1)
    - Williams Service Station (Box 1)
    - WSAM (Box 1)
  - People, 3 prints (Box 1)
  - Residential, 7 prints (Box 1)